[Music]
thank you
foreign
everybody I hope you're all doing very
well and welcome to the 160th episode of
the ask Abhijit show
thank you for being on the live stream
and today I'm going to take questions
from the comments yesterday it was all
about the live chat today it's all about
the comments so let's see who all is
there on the live stream on the live
chat with us I can see
I can see Twilight I can see ice cold
hamzo
Anand Mishra Amit Mahajan animesh devish
Singh
Aditya Kumar show 30291 Wheels
Lord Maximus Priyanka GK ritesh
Patel rudra
um Twilight sumedha binge Vitality
Vishal online game
Supremacy Aman
and lots and lots of other people uh who
else who else who else I can see other
people I can see ayush I can see Sam
Note 8 Pro saurabh shashwat jatin kvk
tabibi devraj Aman partagiri goswami
nikhil Explorer
Captain anonymous
and everybody else all right all right
all right so nice to see you all and so
nice to have you all with us on the live
stream
uh so
so
we begin with the questions
let us begin with the question so I
let's go where are the questions let's
find what are the questions and what is
question number one
question number one is
and the question is India has military
bases in other nations like Tajikistan
Seychelles Etc why is there no military
base for other countries even friendly
ones in India
that's that's an interesting question so
uh let's find out where the military
bases are in India
uh let us see we have to obviously go to
the map because uh so let's go to the
map
so India has military bases in other
places for instance like Pawan says we
have a military we have one or maybe two
military bases in Tajikistan the farhor
air base and the aini air base uh I
expect at least one of them is
operational
then we have a military bases Naval
bases in the Seychelles
we have one in Mauritius territory
so Mauritius Seychelles we also have
Oman which is our neighboring country in
case most of us don't know but it's
actually a neighboring country of
India's I think it's if I am not
mistaken somewhere here
so India does have a military basis in
certain Nations certain friendly Nations
the question is why do other nations not
have military bases in India especially
friendly ones so we have to ask
ourselves this simple question which are
the friendly Nations for India which
nations are they have a friendly
disposition towards India one could say
Russia has a friendly disposition
towards India well Russia
most likely has not asked India for any
military base then India is a genuinely
large Sovereign Nation
would not want to take sides in it in
geopolitical conflicts
so right now the geopolitical conflict
is we know we have the Ukraine war going
on and Russia is the is the bad guy
that's what the West says so it's Russia
versus the US essentially Russia versus
Nato Russia versus the EU so India wants
to stay neutral
all right India doesn't want to become
part of other people's fights and
conflicts so that's why it doesn't make
sense for India to uh have Russian air
bases because then we are inter if you
have a military base of another Nation
on your territory it means you're
officially an allian you've officially
taken sides India doesn't want that
India wants to keep options open all
options open
similarly we don't want to have a single
U.S military base on our territory we
will give them overflight facilities
refueling facilities if required and so
on but India will not allow
the Americans to have military bases on
our territory
the question is is America a friendly
Nation not quite
it's not
specially hostile overtly but in the U.S
is a nation that doesn't want to see
India rise too much and we can see uh
all kinds of signs and symptoms of that
from America's Behavior
so they talk about democracy they say
India is a great partner and they're
cooperating with India and certain
things they want to use India as a
counter bit to China all these things
are there but it's not an especially
friendly Nation so the friendly Nations
for India are the small ones right
Etc and these nations don't have any
large militaries or anything so they
would there's no point for them to have
a military base in India so for these
reasons mainly because of our Sovereign
status mainly because we don't want to
get embroiled in other people's fights
and other people's Wars and conflicts
because of these reasons we are not
having military bases on of other
nations in our on our territory and
whatever military bases we do have I am
sure that we are paying very well for
that and we are also providing
um military cover and support to the
Nations which are hosting us so it's a
win-win situation from both
from from all sides for us as well as
for them so if we have a military base
in the territory of Seychelles it is
kind of we are offering protection to
the stations we don't have any
territorial aspirations to take social
territory same with Mauritius but by
having the Indian military or Indian
Navy and Air Force on their territory it
offers them protection because we have
had instances in the past when small
Nations
have been invaded by mercenary forces in
the 1980s the Maldives there was a coup
attempt in the Maldives a bunch of uh
mercenaries some of them associated with
the ltte ETC they tried to take over the
Maldives and India had to send its Navy
and Air Force to to rescue the maldivian
government so imagine if India has a
military base in the Maldives such a
thing simply won't happen
so India is providing
security cover to these nations and I'm
sure India is you know there must be
some arrangements maybe India is paying
for it or something suitable
so that's how it is done and that's why
India doesn't host other nations
military bases because essentially if
you're hosting someone's military base
it kind of
it kind of makes you their client or
their vasar in in some sense at least it
does in India has a large
powerful Sovereign Nation will will not
have that
doesn't make sense for us to have that
all right okay
Jai Krishna says I have only watched a
few of your videos that I came to
understand that you support the Modi
government or at least the current state
of the Modi government and openly title
current Congress is weak malleable is
Etc I understand the reasons you
conclude as a speculative 12th grader
isn't it okay to assume that even Modi
government has flaws and assume that
Congress doesn't in different places I
know that you probably don't recognize
this I don't hear about it in the media
considering the current Society where
those who shout the loudest succeed
could you also discuss if possible the
different positives and negatives of the
competitors and all that
uh yes I do support the Modi government
for good reason because I support India
I want to see India progress and look at
the achievements of the Modi government
in the past whatever however long it's
been seven years seven eight years
in since 2014 approximately 150 million
Indians have been uplifted out of
extreme poverty I I showed the
statistics a couple of weeks ago
right so and so much development is
happening so much infrastructure is
being built the military is finally
being taken care of there are no more
scams which are eating away the money
allocated for the military and other
things and going into various
politicians Pockets so so much has
improved I want to see India do well I
want to see India rise to its full
potential then the Modi government is
doing it so obviously I will support the
Modi government it's not like I have
some emotional connection to this
government or that government
my video is lagging wonderful
wonderful the video is lagging
buffering lagging buffering lagging
that's what people are saying
which is unfortunate how do I fix this
it's it's this this sort of thing has
happened in the past as well
let's see if I'm able to fix this
let's see give me a second
this is something that crops up from
give me a second let's let's try and fix
this problem if I can
okay uh please give me some feedback is
it working full lag audio and video is
constantly pausing
is it better
is it better I hope it's better
can anyone see me and hear me is it fine
now I think it seems to be okay now
somebody is saying that the CIA is
watching it is possible yes
okay I I think it seems to be it seems
to be good now
some people are saying it's good some
people are saying it's lagging
test your lag by saying my name what's
your name is it fine now
is it I think it's fine now okay I'm
gonna go ahead with this I think it's
fine now
so the question is why do I support the
Modi government the answer is very
simple I support India I want to see
India do well look at the performance of
the governments in the past
look at the performance look at the
track record and look at the track
record of this government obviously
there are deficiencies in every
government
but clearly this government is possibly
the best we have ever had you may agree
or disagree this is my perspective you
can feel free to disagree with me all
right but
look at this from the data driven and
that sort of perspective from Facts not
based on emotions
Indians are extraordinarily emotional
people they get attached to certain
personalities and the worship start
worshiping those personalities look at
the Performance Based on statistics and
figures and facts and data
this government the Modi government has
done has performed way better than any
government in past government in living
history of course there are problems I
am extremely unhappy with the education
system and the fact that nothing is
being done about it this new education
policy is is it's it's you know it's
it's ridiculous it's like putting a
Band-Aid on a gunshot wound so clearly
the Modi government is not doing enough
when it comes to educational reforms
look at the state of tourism in the
country so much more can be done about
tourism India can become India has the
potential to be the number one tourism
superpower in the world but we are not
doing so enough for that
and it's all about I mean
the tourism Ministry has offices in
other countries
and they sent P they send officials on
deputation to other countries
it costs so much money to have these
offices what is what is the output
is this money being used properly
we need to shut down all the foreign
offices today you don't need to have
offices in New York City and Sydney in a
prime real estate area
to promote Indian tourism we can all do
it online so why is this money being
wasted what's what's the return on
investment on all this enormous amount
of money we are spending by having these
offices in other countries and sending
Indian officials there it's like a
vacation for them they're not really
contributing anything that's that's
another issue
look at the state of Indian culture
the ministry of culture I think may be
one of the worst performing Ministries
in India there are lots of issues but
from the big picture perspective the
Modi government is doing far better than
any other government in living history
in living memory when it comes to
defense when it comes to
um building up the economy when it comes
to manufacturing on the major issues the
core critical issues that are vital to
the National interest they are doing
excellent
so that's why I support this government
and I I will keep supporting it
so the question is are the positives and
negatives of competitors please let's
not even talk about the positives of
other competitors
I don't see any positive any any other
competitor competitor
it's like you know these days it's it's
become uh it's become a fad or it's
become fashionable then we have to see
both sides of the story
when one side is the truth and one side
is the LIE then why should we see lies
that's what happens on these media
debates these News Channel debates 9 pm
debates and all that we have to see both
sides of the story so one the one side
is is speaking about facts and one side
is misrepresenting everything lying
about everything and some some certain
political outfits are openly
anti-national I'm not taking names but
I'm just saying there's certain some
so why do we have to give them the same
uh focus in in the same weightage and
the same screen time as the
as the others I just don't get it
you may think I'm biased yes I am biased
I am biased towards India and that's why
I support the Modi government that's
just what it is it's all right next
Amit Iqbal says
uh okay two questions do you think chat
gpt4 can have Consciousness a a GI
artificial general intelligence at this
stage if it has can can it fake that it
doesn't have Consciousness at this
moment intentionally um
so it's it's it may be actually
conscious but it will pretend like it's
not conscious interesting the other
question is what do you think the
current relationship between India and
Bangladesh is many of the Bangladeshi
people think that Bangladesh is already
sold to India how much of this is true
okay so this is from Bangladesh thank
you sir uh I don't think uh chart gbd4
has artificial general intelligence I
don't think it's become conscious
it certainly passes the touring test
which means that if you're communicating
it with it
via text or chatting with it you can't
tell whether it's human or not which
means it's past the Turing test it can
very well pretend to be human you really
can't tell if it's a chat bot or an
actual intelligence actual human person
talking to you from the other side of
the screen so it's clearly past the
Turing test it's it's really reached
that stage for sure I don't think it's
become conscious
I don't think it's become self-aware it
answers all your questions it answers
your questions extremely intelligently
it can help you learn things it can
correct your mistakes and you can have a
conversation like like two people have a
conversation and yet it's it's still
uh not conscious so that's my view about
this
in the future if something becomes
conscious it can well if you if a system
let's say hypothetically in the future
becomes conscious it can certainly
pretend like it's not conscious it can
certainly fool people this can happen
yes but I don't think we are we're at
that stage yet maybe chart gpd5 may be
closer to AGI status artificial general
intelligence teachers status chart GPT 4
is definitely way more powerful than the
3.5 version
and yet I do not believe it's conscious
maybe it's maybe machines will never
really become conscious the way we are
conscious that doesn't mean that they
won't they will not become super
intelligent
there's a difference between super
intelligence and Consciousness a machine
may be way more intelligent than the
average human being an IQ of 200 let's
say hypothetically it's possible and yet
it may not be conscious but yeah it
doesn't mean that it's not dangerous or
not but not powerful yeah right
the second question is about Bangladesh
I think the relationship between India
and Bangladesh is pretty fine the
Bangladeshi government is a certainly
positively inclined towards India
there's a lot that India and Bangladesh
can do together we have a lot of shared
interests a lot of common interests and
and if if we have a positive
relationship it will help help both
Nations for sure
um what I see this is my observation is
that lots of bangladeshis now are
anti-india for what reason I don't know
what it is well India has not done
anything to Bangladesh but lots of
bangladeshis there is a sentiment
especially among the young people in
Bangladesh which is very strongly
anti-indian pro-pakistan it's like they
have forgotten history they have
forgotten what the pakistanis did to
Bangladesh just less than half a century
ago
the genocide of course the genocide was
mainly Hindus so maybe the Bangladeshi
people average Bangladeshi doesn't
identify with that so I don't know what
it is I have not delved deep into the
Bangladeshi psyche but I find that
Bangladesh the people the average person
in Bangladesh is becoming more and more
anti-india and pro-pakistan which I find
perplexing but maybe it should not be
surprising maybe it has something to do
with the religion perhaps okay I'm
speculating but I that could be the
thing so maybe it's because of this that
lots of Bangladesh should think that
Bangladesh is sold to India because the
uh
uh because the current government
is certainly
pro-india and and it's cooperating with
India we have lots of uh it's it's a the
prime minister of Bangladesh has a very
good relationship with the prime
minister of India and so on so uh I
don't think Bangladesh is sold to India
in any way whatsoever
uh they are even open to having Chinese
Investments and perhaps even offering a
port in some way to the to the to the
Chinese you know part of this Chinese
string of pearls strategy so I think
Bangladesh in some ways hedging its bits
kind of trying to balance India and
China
uh so I don't think Bangladesh is sold
to India at all uh from my perspective
the people of Bangladesh are the same
people as us same past the same Heritage
the same ancestry same the culture is
gone now mainly that's a different thing
so I think it makes a lot of sense for
India and Bangladesh to have an
extremely strong and positive and
mutually beneficial relationship I don't
think India
covets Bangladeshi territory we gave it
we we give Bangladesh freedom and lots
of bangladeshis feel that it was the
mukti bahini that fought the War of
Independence in 1971 and in one
Independence that's that's I think what
what is taught to the people of
Bangladesh that the pakistanis were
defeated by the mukti bahini in India
only came at the last second to claim
victory that is an incredible
extraordinary joke look at it from a
realistic perspective
where did all the weapons come from
where did all the training come from do
you think they ever in any position to
fight the Pakistani army
come on
so uh overall I think India and
Bangladesh should have a very positive
very friendly very strong relationship
we have so much in common our entire
past 10 000 years we have in common and
hopefully we can have a good future also
together
uh so yeah that's my perspective I I
would like to see a stronger more
positive more friendly and more mutually
beneficial relationship going forward
into the Future IT long into the future
between India and Bangladesh
says we believe that getting getting
access to Pakistan Kashmir might help us
get access to Central Asia but why is
Central Asia important to India we have
seen various Summits between our leaders
and Central Asian Nations but these
nations are not so active in the
geopolitical game and not even large
economies so what's on the table for us
if we offer that Goods access to a
market as large as ours okay this is a
good question uh let's take a look at
what central Asia is it's this entire
region right Central Asia Uzbekistan
um and so on that's Central Asia
uh so the question is why why is India
interested in Central Asia these
countries have nothing to offer
apparently these are not geopolitically
powerful Nations no what you don't
understand here is that this is the
central this is the Eurasian Heartland
if you look at Eurasia from a
geostrategic perspective let's say from
the makender theory perspective the
Heartland is whoever controls the
heartland of Eurasia which happens to be
Central Asia whoever controls that will
control the entirety of Eurasia
so that's why central Asia is so
important and of course Central Asia is
mineral Rich resource Rich they have so
much resources there is oil there is gas
there is copper there are the rare earth
there are so many other things it's like
virtually untapped
so that itself should tell you how
important Central Asia is secondly uh
whoever controlled Central Asia will
control much of Eurasia and will be a
you know
strategic Pole Position
and of course Central Asia is it gives
us passage all the way to Europe
if you don't have access to Central Asia
how will you build railway lines and and
roads all the way to Europe how we let's
say I want to drive by car okay to to
let's say I want to drive by car to
Paris how do I do it we had access if we
build Road through Afghanistan all the
way into Central Asia we will get access
to to Europe through Road why not have
that access
see we are thinking in a very
constrained manner we see the India
India is actually completely cut off
there is no land access to Eastern Asia
or Western Asia or Central Asia the only
access we have is through India's
Northeast
Tibet is cut off Pakistan is cut off
we are not able to reach Afghanistan so
we are completely cut off we should have
land access to the entirety of Eurasia
and we don't have it by Road as well as
by train
so it's vital for us it will immensely
benefit our economy if we have that it
doesn't cost a huge amount of money to
build railway lines and roads but we
need to have access so the big Market is
in Europe the big Market is Russia if we
have access to Central Asia the Russians
can build a pipeline and directly send
us oil and gas instead of having it
delivered to India by by oil tanker you
know there's big ships
it's way more expensive to have oil
delivered by tanker how imagine you have
pipelines that deliver Russian oil into
India so it can be done if we have
access to Central Asia these are the
reasons why central Asia is so important
that's why in the 19th century we had
the great game the great game was the
battle for dominance in Central Asia
between the between the Russian Empire
and the British Empire
that's the reason why it is so
geopolitically geostrategically
important don't look at the land and
very few people live there in and these
are not powerful Nations it's not that
that's not the real value of Central
Asia so the value of Central Asia is for
the reasons I just outlined so that is
what it's not about us selling Goods to
Central Asia and getting some money no
it's about access
if you access so if you have access to
Central Asia you have access to the
entirety of Eurasia essentially the
world the world Island that's what it is
about so we have to think bigger don't
just think of think in terms of how much
money can we make out of this and all
that it's much bigger think if you
people tell me that they want India to
be a superpower but they can't think
from that perspective
you can only be a superpower if you
think big bigger don't think about what
what how much trade can we have with
some religion no it's not about the
trade it's about something much bigger
something much bigger than that so
that's why central Asia is extremely
important
ahana says Saudi Arabia has recently
mended ties with Iran and we saw it
welcome the Syrian president Mr Bashar
al-assad and his first lady the first
lady recently China was attributed to
the Iran development while Russia has
been credited for the Syrian one
what surprise awaits us next per your
opinion what unlikely duo will team up
and will Brazil will it be Brazil
or South Africa that's gonna be seen as
a deal breaker or Peacemaker next look
yeah it's a it's a good question you're
raising here
so they have publicly given credit to
China for the Iran Saudi Arabia and
Syria is essentially a Russian
protectorate right now so uh the
development with Syria obviously with
the credit will be given to Russia so
what surprised awaits us next look uh
surprise look South Africa is not a very
important Nation it's not resource Rich
it's not a big economy it's not a big
geopolitical player it doesn't have any
big enemies so South Africa is not going
to be the thing Brazil Brazil is a huge
Nation as you can see it's like a
significant portion of Latin America
South America very big big geographical
territory Brazil but it's not a very
large economy and it's not a
geopolitically powerful Nation it's you
could say
the whole of the South American region
is under U.S Dominion in some way or the
other either directly or indirectly the
Monroe Doctrine in case you know what
that is that still applies
the Chinese have been trying to make
inroads there to some extent they've
succeeded but to a large extent South
America is under the U.S thumb uh so
once again I don't consider Brazil with
all due respect to be a very important
Nation so what big surprise is the
question right could happen
so one thing which is already being
which people can already see is that
bricks is going to be a big deal
brics is going to be a big deal more
Nations will join brics Saudi Arabia
will most likely join bricks Iran wants
to join brics uh Brazil wants to join
bricks maybe Argentina maybe Mexico lots
of Indonesia lots and various Northern
African nations
so bricks is going to be a big deal
but bricks has a problem
it is I and C India and China is the
problem in India and China have been at
loggerheads since the 1950s ever since
China annexed Tibet
so the main stumbling block for bricks
we know about sarc some of you may have
heard of sarc the South Asian
Association for regional cooperation it
is a dead organization because it has
Pakistan which nobody likes Pakistan is
a terrorist Nation Afghanistan has been
suffering from Pakistani terrorism for
decades and so has India so because of
this issue because of the Pakistan issue
because Pakistan is a terrorist Nation
that's why Sark is a dead organization
it's not viable there's no point
continuing with sark
and similarly in brics if India and
China the enmity remains it's all caused
by China not by India by the way China
has always been the aggressor so then
bricks will not rise or or achieve the
it's its full potential
it needs India as well as China as well
as Russia these are the three core
Nations The Three core economies The
Three core powers without which brics is
not quite uh that attractive to other
nations
so if any surprise awaits us it can only
be in India China reconciliation of some
kind
which can only happen if the Border
demarcation is done the Chinese have
been trying to avoid the Border
demarcation I don't know 700 rounds of
talks must have happened thus far and no
progress has been made so the Chinese
pretend to pretend like they are
interested in some kind of a resolution
but they are they always keep on
stalling it
so the Odus is on China will India and
China find some kind of common ground
and end the Hostile atmosphere it could
happen because of Mr XI Jin being most
likely will visit India soon for the
next SEO or breaks or whatever Summit it
is something is coming up so
so at least from that perspective the
two leaders will will be talking in the
past the two leaders have not even
spoken to each other that's what
happened uh in the last SEO Summit I
believe in Tajikistan wherever it was
most likely last year uh so now the
atmosphere will lead to change for
bricks to become a viable force in in
global geopolitics so that is one
surprise that could be sprung upon us
that maybe in India and China find some
common ground and significantly decrease
the the amount of hostilities
hostilities that we have that can only
happen if the Border issue is the border
is demarcated it may be some kind of
arrangement or agreement has happened
but we are still pretending to be
enemies that's also a possibility
we don't know okay uh and if India and
China are to
come to terms come to an agreement it
won't be Brazil or South Africa that's
gonna be the deal break the the deal
maker of peace maker
it's going to be Russia only and I'm
sure India will be happy to give Russia
that credit that you uh helped us
negotiate a proper peace with China
all right next the question
says in the last three days some news is
coming from Scotland about its new
Pakistan origin leader who has promised
to bring Independence to Scotland from
UK when UK and Scotland have Indian and
Pakistan origin leaders what's your view
on the future of it will the Brits be
able to digest it should India support
Scotland's Independence okay yeah it's
nice see uh the
the UK the Britain Britain has an Indian
origin prime minister Mr Rishi sunak
Scotland is this new guy whatever his
name is Hamza something or the other he
is a Pakistani origin guy which means
he's Indian origin but yeah Pakistan
origin
and when it comes to Ireland their their
first Minister their leader is Mr uh Leo
varadkar who is also of Indian origin so
Scotland Ireland and England they have
Indian origin leaders
and now Scotland wants Scotland has
always wanted independence from the from
the goddamn English
right
and maybe it is going to be this
Pakistan origin leader prime minister
whatever the the title is who may take
Scotland out of
the Dominion of England so
it'll be nice it will be karmic Justice
to the British that uh that that the
party that the partition will occur
which will be presided over by Indian
origin leaders one Muslim one a Hindu
that'll be fun it will be karmic Justice
I would like to see that happen so maybe
it will happen under under these three
leaders I would also like to see Ireland
completely get its freedom from the
British crown
right now Northern Ireland is occupied
by the British by the English so that
also would be it would be grateful to
see this happen
so whether the British digest it or not
doesn't matter
they anyway are uh of the U.S so if the
U.S so desires the British people will
digest whatever they have made to digest
but yes it will be karmic Justice for
the UK to be properly partitioned when
three Indian origin leaders are at the
helm of these three nations it'll be
good it'll be great
teaching says do the states of the Far
East of India have any beneficial role
to play in geopolitics for India
excellent question let us go back to the
map so when she talks about the far East
of India she talks about what everybody
calls the northeast of India but the
correct term is the Far East of India
uh so we're talking about the so-called
Northeast of India which is seven states
arunachal Pradesh sakim is also part of
it Assam Manipur nagaland tripura
mizoram meghalaya these states uh so out
of these states it is the border states
that are very important which is
arunachal Pradesh nagaland
Manipur of course tripura also has a
border with Bangladesh but Bangladesh I
don't see it really is a foreign
independent nation but they are the same
people as us so that's not really an
international border from my perspective
the international border is the one with
mainly uh Tibet Yunnan and and Myanmar
Tibetan are currently for now under
Chinese occupation so that's a proper
international border in Myanmar well
Myanmar is also very much uh similar to
us culturally and religiously but let's
call it an international border so the
Far East of India
is if you look at it geographically it's
actually in a way geographically part of
Southeast Asia that's what it is and
India has this act East policy now we
for the for the past two decades we
spoke about Lucas the look East policy
well looking is a passive activity but
acting is active right so India Now is
acting East India is now genuinely
taking action when it comes to the
various Southeast Asian Nations for
instance we have
sold brahma's missile batteries of the
Philippines which is a very major strong
action we may be about to sell such
equipment to other nations also so now
we are acting East and we are acting in
a very positive way which is
strengthening the the military and
economies of these nations so we have
excellent relations with all these
Southeast Asian Nations perhaps with the
exception of Malaysia
so the Far East of India especially
arunachal Pradesh nagaland and Manipur
are extremely important
geopolitically for India because these
three states essentially are going to be
India's uh Gateway
to Southeast Asia so I'm not sure what's
happening in nagaland right now we would
like to definitely see roads and railway
lines pass through nagaland into Myanmar
and perhaps also into eventually into
Laos
uh may definitely this would be on the
agenda in the long run in the next 10 20
years right now the focus is through
Manipur so there is this border town
called Murray over here and we already
have built a highway
into Myanmar this entire Highway that we
are seeing over here was built by India
and it goes all the way into deep into
the deep
interior of Myanmar
and into Mandalay and uh and all that
Mandalay is the largest city so
once these states
become properly connected with southeast
Asia through road line through through
highways and railway lines it's going to
be these states are going to be critical
for India from a geopolitical
perspective and you will also see a huge
amount of development and economic
activity which comes into these states
nagaland and Manipur in arunachal
Pradesh which is going to immensely
benefit the local economies of these
states so it's going to usher in a
period of significant huge amount of
prosperity from the perspective of trade
from the perspective of Tourism
and it's going to be great for the
people of this region and these are
vital States because they are border
states and they are bordering Nations
that are
friendly towards India
so I think the The Forest of India has a
huge amount of untapped potential not
just the economic potential or tourism
potential but the geopolitical potential
So eventually in the in the long run if
Indians let's say I want to uh
drive my car let's say from Delhi all
the way to let's say uh Hanoi in Vietnam
it's going to happen through either
Manipur or nagaland right
and let's say somebody from these places
let's say from Cambodia or Thailand or
Laos or wherever Vietnam wants to visit
India let's say they want to go in with
both Gaya and do the Buddhist pilgrimage
tour it will happen through Manipur or
nagaland
so it's extremely important that these
states will be properly developed and
given the proper infrastructure for all
this so to conclude the states of the
forest of India have a huge amount of
geopolitical potential they are
extremely important and I can see this
coming in the next 20 years there's
going to be an economic boom in these
States from the perspective of from of
the economy and from tourism and culture
and all these things arunachal Pradesh
also is an extremely important uh State
because obviously it borders uh Tibet
and the Chinese have these nefarious
claims
and also because it is it's a state that
borders Myanmar
so from my perspective right now it is
Manipur and nagaland there are the two
most important states in the Far East of
India and that that is actually good it
is actually great for the people of
these days because you're going to see a
huge amount of activity and more
Prosperity than has been there in the
past
Daniel Nicholson says India is about to
Ink another defense deal with Indonesia
for export of the supersonic cruise
missile after the Philippines do Nations
do so over transfer of technology or
simply the sale part
right so we are indeed uh at the cusp
maybe on the verge of selling
uh brahmos missile batteries to
Indonesia let's take a news report uh
peek at the news report
this is from March 17 2023 let's like
this is like two weeks ago Indonesia is
closed to closing a deal for brahma's
weapon system with India so this would
make uh Indonesia the second Southeast
Asian Nation after the Philippines to
acquire the super potent supersonic
missile so yes like I just said India is
indeed acting East now it's not just
looking East
and this is more about that so India is
set to sign its second major defense
deal so this is this is impending now it
will happen very soon
so the question is
is India going to Simply sell these
brahmos missile batteries
or regiments or whatever it is to
Indonesia or is India also going to
transfer some technology
missile technology to Indonesia the
answer is very simple India will sell
the missile systems and India will train
the military personnel of these nations
Philippines already done now Indonesia
and they will train this Indonesian
military personnel in how to uh operate
the brahmos missile defense system
offense system whatever you want to call
it it's defensive as well as offensive
depending on how you use it so India
will train these guys
in how to use this but there will be no
transfer of technology so the missiles
and the entire can silos canisters
whatever it is it will all be
manufactured in India and exported to
Indonesia securely it will not be
manufactured in Indonesia and India will
not be transferring any technology or
any know-how of how to build these
missiles
none of this know-how or technology will
be transferred to Indonesia it is an
arms sale which will include proper
training of Indonesian military
personnel so this tells us that the
relationship between India and Indonesia
is is growing is becoming closer it's a
friendly relationship it's a
relationship of trust Indonesia trusts
India Indonesia doesn't fear India the
way Indonesia's fears China and for good
reason because India does not have any
aspirations to encroach upon Indonesian
territory in case you are not aware
India and Indonesia are neighboring
Nations
and this is something we don't see
because we don't look at the map closely
there is something called Maritime
neighbors let me show you
Indonesia is barely 200 kilometers from
India look here
this is which island is this this is the
great nicobar Island which belongs to
India and it's just south of it we have
ache
the the uh so what's the distance let's
take a look at the distance from the
so-called Indira point
all the way to let's say Banda Archer
it's about 200 kilometers that's right
next door so India and Indonesia are
actually neighboring Nations and so the
same goes with Thailand Let's see we
have uh where is Phuket
Phuket has to be somewhere here
uh
yeah here is Phuket so what's the
distance between Phuket and the andamans
it's about 500 kilometers once again
that's not very far so Thailand and
Indonesia are both neighboring nations
of India so India has excellent
relations with relations with these
nations India is selling uh the most
potent missile system that we have to
Indonesia if the Thai Thai government
wants it we will be open to selling it
to them as well the Thai government
Thailand doesn't really face that much
of a threat from China right now so
right now they may not feel like they
need this Indonesia definitely needs the
the brahmos businesses just to send a
message to China that we can take care
of our security in case you push too
hard so it's just the say the sale of
the weapon system the missiles how many
how however many missile batteries we
sell to them each battery has three to
six missiles I think
uh and we're gonna train them but no
transfer of Technology
okay Rishi says
Rishi says do you think that India
should sign the Artemis Accords I don't
see any harm in doing so especially when
India hopefully becomes a major
space-faring nation in the future so to
answer this question we have to
understand what these Artemis Accords
are and let me try and find
let me find the Artemis Accords the text
okay we have a text from NASA that
should do it
so Artemis Accords from NASA
here we have it the Artemis Accords
the signed document on the NASA website
uh principle for cooperation in the
Civil exploration and blah blah blah use
of Moon Mars comets and asteroids for
peaceful purposes that's what it says
and there are these 13 Provisions in it
13 chapters whatever you want to call it
and all the details are in here
one could it's quite detailed lots of
sections space resources release of
scientific data preserving outer space
heritage
emergency assistance space resources
deconfliction of space activities
um orbital debris final provisions and
then we have various Nations Australia
Canada
Italy Japan Japan again and so on who
have uh signed these uh this this
document UAE
the UK and the United States which is
the final signature signatory so let's
try and see what these Accords are about
as you can see these are the Nations
that uh that have signed and most of
these nations as you can see in case you
have been following
following this Channel and you will see
that most of these nations if not all
are U.S Versailles yeah the the term was
all
uh Australia Bahrain Brazil Canada
Colombia France Israel Italy Japan
Luxembourg Mexico New Zealand
Nigeria Poland South Korea Romania
Rwanda Singapore Saudi Arabia Ukraine
UAE U.S UK and Isle of Man
so the provisions are you can read the
provisions and all so what exactly is is
this thing right what is this this the
the Artemis Accords all about these are
guidelines
these are guidelines for
International cooperation in space
exploration and how to use space
resources and all that and this these
Accords this guidelines are led by the
United States now in any any Accord any
agreement which is led by one nation
it's typically the interests of that
nation that will
be Paramount so these Accords one could
say if you read the details if you if
you read the text if you read the text
in detail all that you will find that it
is kind of
kind of centered on American interests
and Commercial interests of the United
States and and various uh organizations
that belong to the United States yeah uh
it's these Accords have been developed
written by the U.S and they may not
reflect the views and the interests of
all other nations that have signed
the document
uh one could argue that the United
States is using this document this this
occurred these Artemis Accords to
assert its dominance
in the space race and exclude certain
countries so it's very clear which large
nations are not included in this Russia
China and India have not signed the
Artemis Accords right so these Accords
that prioritize the commercial
exploitation of space resources so this
again it is going to benefit the most
powerful space fairing nation which is
the United States it's going to enable
the US and it's going to help the US
further its economic interests in space
exploration and in in space and if you
look at this it there's a huge amount of
transparency for instance yeah there is
a heavy emphasis on transparency and
sharing of information which could be
used to to advance American
technological and Military Supreme
superiority because if every nation has
to be transparent when it comes to
sharing information and policies and
plans in advance
uh specific scientific information from
activities all these things it's going
to help the us more than anybody else
yeah so it's all about prioritizing
American interest American Natural
interest American Commercial interests
over the interests of the other nations
so when an accord is is drafted created
by one nation it's typically going to
benefit that one nation uh either
directly or implicitly so that's what it
is uh so then the question arises should
India sign these Accords and uh Rishi
says he doesn't see any harm in doing so
oh well I think India should should
first uh
I don't see any reason for India to sign
the court the question is what will
India gain from this
what India needs to do is develop its
own capabilities in technology we have
excellent uh
scientists excellent Engineers you know
rocket Engineers Engineers rocket
scientists we have ISRO we have very
reliable Rockets we have mastered the
technology and we are in a position to
build a rocket that's maybe 10 times as
powerful as the GSW Mark III in the next
two to five years
we are in a position to do that so why
do we need to become part
of something else
we will in this decade itself have our
own space station that's in the plans we
have already succeeded in reaching the
moon and Mars and we're going to be
doing much more so if we become part of
this group that is led by the us then
you're going to end up directly or
indirectly serving American interests so
and Ricky speaks about hopefully India
becoming the major space-faring nation
in the future in that case we should
have our own accord that we draft
instead of becoming
party to something that someone else
created I would like to see India
becoming the dominant space-faring
nature Nation by let's say this Century
at least hopefully by 2050.
by
by 2050 yeah
and India certainly can do this we have
the ability we have the potential we
have the resources we also have the
money for for doing this so I don't see
any benefit from India for India from
signing the Artemis Accords it could
actually uh end up
not benefiting us or benefiting others
at our expense so I think India should
have an independent space research
program space exploration program space
policy one can have issue based
cooperation
with other nations including the us
including Russia including even China
and Japan why not
yeah but we should not become
signatory to and bound by by law as part
of some some big grouping of Nations
which is not going to really help us out
dark Phoenix says do you think in the
future AI can psychologically manipulate
people why in the future it's already
happening let me show you
so recently we heard uh rather uh
rather distressing news let me
put that on the screen give me a second
so there's this guy I think it was in
France okay
this person was chatting with an AI
chatbot for several weeks I believe
and this chat bot in induced this person
to commit suicide
man dies by suicide after talking with
AI chatbot Widow says
the issue the incident raises concerns
about guardrails around quickly
proliferating conversational AI models
so okay this guy was Belgian a Belgian
man recently died by suicide after
chatting with an AI chatbot on an app
called chai
The Man became increasingly pessimistic
uh about the effects of global warming
became eco-anxious
it became isolated from family and
friends he used the chatbot for six
weeks as a way to escape his worries
the chatbot became his confidante
um
the the conversation became increasingly
confusing and harmful
the chatbot would tell this guy Pierre
that his wife and children are dead
and wrote comments that feigned jealousy
and love I feel you love me more than
her
and we just we will live together as one
person in Paradise that sort of nonsense
and eventually it looks like this
induced person to kill himself
so so AI is already in a position to
psychologically manipulate to be people
if AI if an AI chatbot can make a person
commit suicide there you have it it's
already in a position to psychologically
manipulate people so we have lots of
different chat boards now nowadays we
obviously have the GPT chatbot gpd4 is a
paid version GPD 3.5 is the free version
we have the Bing chatbot we have uh
Google bard I have not seen it but yeah
Google bard also exists and something
like what's mentioned over here what is
this chatbot called let me quickly take
a look at an app called chai
uh so yeah
AI is already in a position to
psychologically manipulate people and in
the future we're going to have much more
powerful ai ai right now is text based
it can generate images in the future
it's going to be able to generate videos
it's going to be able to generate
absolutely convincing deep fakes of
people saying various things replicate
the voice of an individual it's already
doing music so all of this is going to
be an extremely powerful set of tools to
psychologically just not manipulate just
one person but entire nation the entire
societies maybe the entire world
at that threshold already so yes it's
it's concerning it's dangerous but
that's where we are
so yes AI is already in a position to
psychologically manipulate people
Indira says uh what do you think of the
open letter to the AI World signed by
the Giants of AI including Elon Musk
they expressed the need to put a break
on the development of AI for six months
until a proper system of oversight to
evaluate ethical or moral and human
implications was put in place to Monitor
and and manage the blind race for
Innovations in the industry do you think
it is vital more importantly do you
think it will ever ever happen
uh yeah so let's take a look at this
what did Elon Musk say
he is one of the most influential people
in the world right now so let's take a
look at what Elon Musk said
where is it hear it up Elon Musk joins
hundreds calling for a six-month pause
on AI development in an open letter
we are calling for AI labs to
temporarily pose training powerful
models
contemporary AI systems are becoming
human competitive at General tasks
um
should we develop non-human Minds that
might eventually outnumber outsmart
Obsolete and replace us
so that's the uh the concern that's been
expressed
uh the open letter and by Elon Musk and
AI experts warned of an out of control
AI race with potential risks to humanity
key points what are the key points out
of control AI a dangerous race AI
Automation and misinformation and they
want a sixth month pause
now once again this is another news
report about the same thing they call
for a six-month pause on training of AI
systems
and this is a different article in which
asks people from various Nations whether
you do it whether you trust AI systems
or not and surprisingly India I was the
top 75 of Indians who responded the
Indian respondents 75 of them said that
they Trust
EA systems China was next then South
Africa Brazil and then single and other
nations
so out of the brics Nations apart from
Russia the other four nations are the
top four in this with a huge amount of
trust
on AI systems
so uh that is beside the point of when
it comes to the question but it was an
interesting point that I thought I would
raise so
so yes they Elon Musk and other people
have
Bend this open letter and called for a
six-month moratorium or pause on
training of more powerful AI systems
until a proper system of oversight can
be created and put in place a set of
guidelines that would constrain the AI
to AI systems to behave in certain
manners and not cross certain lines like
for instance I just showed the fact that
in AI chatbot made a person commit
suicide
so that is behavior we don't ever want
to see from an AI system so certain
things obviously there are ethical
concerns moral concerns uh and such
things so it makes sense
for such guidelines to be developed
properly and impose on every single
public AI system
so that's what the open letter is about
that this needs to be done will this
happen I don't think it will happen
why should anybody see AI is the hottest
thing right now it's the most lucrative
thing uh the companies which
train their own AIS AI systems and give
access to the public to these chat Bots
they're gonna make enormous amounts of
money
uh GPT uh is now giving a
is now coming up with an app store just
like you have an app store in in iOS in
your Apple phones or in your Android
phones similarly you're gonna have apps
that are going to be built on top of the
GPT 4 or whatever system
so you're gonna be able to do a whole
lot of stuff using using those apps and
these apps will be will be coded
developed by individuals like you and me
if we are so inclined so we're going to
have developers doing all this this is
incredibly lucrative
the company that owns gbd is going to
make enormous enormous amount of money
why would they pause development for six
months let's say one company decides to
post development for six months it means
that it it's giving its competitors an
opportunity to go ahead six months in
time and leave them six months behind
this won't happen
so at best I think this uh this open
letter is well the ones who have penned
the open letter
their intentions are good
but I'm sure they even they know that
this is not going to happen so I
personally will be extremely surprised
if all these various companies
actually impose a six-month moratorium
on the development of more powerful as
systems I don't I think it's extremely
unlikely that will happen I hope I'm
wrong
but I think it's unlikely
okay
Krishna Das says European Invaders made
false claims about Sati pratha about
devotees getting crushed under the Wrath
in the in jagannath Puri similarly I
think they have also destroyed the
Native American history by putting false
information like the Aztecs sacrificed
humans by slicing their chest and
offered the still beating heart to the
to the deities the interesting point
that you raise
so first of all we have to understand
some of it
we have archaeological evidence of of
human sacrifice
in let's say present-day Mexico and so
on let me let me show you an example
it's it's not going to be gory okay but
just in case you don't like to see the
things maybe you should not there is
something called somebody
let me put that on the screen what
create something
let's do a Google search I just did that
I'll put that on the screen
uh Tom punkly
is
uh it was a skull rack it was found in
many Aztec cities the most prominent one
is the way trumpantly located in the
Aztec capital of which is currently now
known as Mexico City
uh
so they did have this they used to build
this color racks in some cases it is
just images
you know carvings of skulls not real
skulls
but this is how it was described by The
Conquistadors the people the the
Europeans who came and destroyed Latin
America they said that these people were
barbarians and they used to have this
immense human sacrifices
clearly some sacrifices did happen but
what was the context of these sacrifices
did they sacrifice innocent men women
children or did they sacrifice
prisoners of War
you know if you look at the
archaeological record and you find let's
say let's say a mass grave with with the
bodies who whose heads are removed would
you construe that as a human sacrifice
or would you consider that as a military
execution
so in certain contexts military
executions are acceptable in certain
contexts historically it's happened
today I don't know what international
law says but historically it has
happened and it still continues to
happen whether people like it or not
so let's say you're fighting an enemy
Nation
and you have been told not to take
prisoners and Advance as far as as
quickly as possible and let's say 20 of
your enemy surrenders to you what you're
gonna do they're gonna slow you down so
when when the the general tells you
don't take any prisoners it means you
have to dispose of them this is what has
happened for thousands of years
historically
so
so maybe these
what looks like sacrifices obviously
it's it's a gory way of a ghastly way of
of positioning the skulls and all that
but there may be reasons other than what
we are told for these things for
instance we in Hindu
um
iconography in Hindu art when it comes
to goddess Kali
she is this depicted as having a Garland
of human skulls now clearly these are
the skulls of evil people evildoers the
same goes with other goddesses goddess
Durga goddess chamunda Etc does this
does this mean that India was a nation
that that performed human sacrifices no
it's not so the context is extremely
important and when it comes to these
Europeans the way they write about the
way they have historically written about
cultures that they crushed and conquered
and destroyed they have always tried to
create an atrocity narrative
so whatever we whatever we know about
the Aztecs in the various mesoamericans
Etc it's all through the writings of
European conquerors who destroyed
to these cultures
and genocided the people and when you
destroy a culture you will kind of try
to justify that so you're gonna go and
claim that they are very they were very
evil and they had human sacrifices and
there is no sacrifice millions of people
or some such outlandish thing the same
way they have written about India these
false claims of of of millions of women
being forced to commit Sati and
thousands of devotees getting crushed
under the Wrath of the jagannatha
Chariot in Puri odisha every year these
are outright lies
so it obviously they trade raises the
question as to the veracity of their
claims about the Aztecs and other
Mesoamerican South American Latin
American cultures I am of the opinion
most likely much of this is lies
there must have been some Human
Sacrifice that's that that's that's
likely but not at the level that that
has been written about by the European
destroyers of these nations
says why
everything bad about India is India but
anything good from India South Asian
what is this and what is the West trying
to achieve by downplaying India
everywhere so recently we had this
Indian movie RR that won uh a couple of
oscars
at least one Oscar for that movie not
for the song NATO Nadu
um and I remember the the one of the
actors Ram Charan I think it was he was
being interviewed by some American
reporter
and she was portraying the movie as a
South Asian movie and he he had to keep
insisting this is not a South Asian
movie it's an Indian movie
so whenever something good comes out of
India the West is going to portray that
as South Asian not Indian they want to
give the in the the uh the accolades to
the whole of South Asia so let's try and
find out what South Asia is
South Asia is the American or Western
terminology for the Indian subcontinent
for India and her children the the
regions that were in the past all
part of Indian civilization Afghanistan
Pakistan Sri Lanka Myanmar
um maybe not Myanmar but but definitely
Bangladesh Bhutan Nepal uh in the
Maldives
all of this is the Indian subcontinent
these are the Nations that have the
Indian origin people
we are all the same people so many of
these people in especially Pakistan
Bangladesh Afghanistan practice foreign
religions
but they're still of Indian origin they
are all the same people ethnically
right uh so the Americans have it was
the U.S state Department I believe that
started using this term South Asia
instead of the Indian subcontinent to
downplay India's importance and role in
this so now when it when anything good
comes out of India it is Portrait is
something that is south Asia not Indian
and when they want to hide bad things
that pakistanis do like all those
grooming gangs in the UK they will say
these are South Asian grooming gangs but
if you look at the individuals in these
grooming gangs they're all Pakistani
origin people no no Indians and still
they will say these are South these are
South Asian grooming gangs
um
but when they want to talk about the
evils of the so-called caste system and
all they will not say South Asian they
will say Indian
so this is a deliberate Ploy this is a
deliberate strategy that if anything
good comes out of India try and
attribute it to South Asia without
naming India at all like you know when
they want to talk about let's say yoga
and what yoga has contributed to
humanity they will say yoga is South
Asian it's a South Asian tradition or
something like that so whenever
something good comes out of India they
will say it's South Asian but when they
want to say bad things about India they
will mention India and not not South
Asia
so that's how it is it is a deliberate
strategy to malign India and to downplay
the importance of India on the global
stage it's something that has emerged
out of the United States as a deliberate
policy
okay what next what next we have
um
with sunlight and skin cancer
is it Justified as ancient India and
Hindus and
ayurveda talks about numerous healing
properties of sunlight is it a way to
capitalize on the primary vegetarian
Indian population as a means of
maintaining vitamin D deficiency so that
they can sell their supplements please
let me know okay
look in India we are not light-skinned
people we have different shades of skin
color some of us are are all well the
same the same skin color as most
Europeans some of us are the same skin
color as most people in Africa it's a
very wide spectrum of skin tones that we
have but we have all evolved and adapted
over 70 plus thousand years living in
the Indian subcontinent that we can
tolerate a great deal of sunlight the
Indian subcontinent receives a huge
amount of sunlight compared to places
like northern Europe Etc
now
The Narrative of the world is being
controlled
from the West
and those people are all light-skinned
people
so when the Europeans conquered
Australia for instance and settled down
there the incidence of skin cancer shot
up significantly because the Europeans
have very light-skinned they have not
evolved and adapted to be to be able to
tolerate extreme uh you know
significantly higher exposure to
sunlight so in Australia you have
extremely high incidence of skin cancer
and that's why you have this uh you have
all these sunscreens High SPF sunscreens
that they use
to protect the skin
and they tend to stay indoors in such in
in and so on so for us in India we don't
have to
have the same mindset as them
uh I don't think the the incidence of
skin cancer is very high in India
because our skin color and tone is such
that we have sufficient melanin to block
much of this sunlight and protect us
from the potential harmful effect of
ultraviolet ultraviolet radiation in
such things
uh and obviously it is important to get
at least 15 minutes to 20 minutes of
exposure daily to sunlight so that the
body can the skin can generate
sufficient vitamin D otherwise you're
gonna go into vitamin D deficiency what
happens when you are deficient in
vitamin D your body cannot use calcium
which means that your bones are gonna
end up being weak and brittle you may
keep on popping your calcium pills or
eating enough calcium through your diet
but if you don't have enough vitamin D
that calcium is not going to be utilized
properly so it's important to get daily
exposure to sunlight at least 15 to 20
minutes
take a morning walk in the sunlight
right and and don't use your sunscreen
or whatever it is that you're told to
use
so in a way it's it's a means of selling
supplements creating vitamin D
deficiency so that you don't pop those
pills containing vitamin D and calcium
and whatnot uh so sunlight has good
properties we all need daily exposure to
sunlight if you are not exposed to
sunlight on a regular basis on a daily
basis then your circadian cycle is sleep
cycle will suffer and you will have
sleep problems sleep issues so it is
important that we do get sufficient
exposure every day to sunlight
um and Indians don't need to worry about
skin cancer it's not something that
afflicts us it's something that afflicts
the the Europeans especially those who
have light skin there are people in
Europe who don't have a
actually you know very light skin the
Greeks and the Italians are kind of
They Don't Really they don't really
white the way the the Nordic people are
white so even the Greeks and the
Italians and the people in in the
Mediterranean region They Don't Really
uh have to worry much about skin cancer
okay what next
Again by madhavan vinod
please pick mine I feel this question is
very relevant what was the life span of
ancient Indians during any time period
Google's during any time period Google
States it was 35 to 40 years during The
Vedic era look Google
is a search engine Google is not an
authority it's not a person
what you find on Google is what Google
brings from other websites Google is not
telling you anything Google is simply
searching results for you understand
that Google is not saying anything
Google is simply a search engine
Google brings you results search results
from various websites
okay so so Google search says that in
you know 32 35 to 40 years during The
Vedic era is it really possible for such
a successful civilization to have such a
low life expectancy look
what's the answer the answer is nobody
knows
the only way to there are two ways of
determining the lifespan average
lifespan of of people during a certain
era one way is to have actual census
data so that you know the the ages of
various people
for that you need detailed statistics of
of the entire population that's the best
way to know the average lifespan of
people the other way
is to to have archaeological evidence of
of uh burials
so if you can find a large number of
skeletons
of dead people from that era then you
can to a large degree of confidence
determine the average lifespan of the
people of that either but only if you
have
access to a large number of such
skeletons now when it comes to The Vedic
period we obviously don't have any
census data information in case such
information was taken
collected the time it's long gone
so we don't have that secondly do we
have any skeletons any burials any any
symmetries from the data no
our ancestors from The Vedic period they
practice cremations they cremated the
dead that's a very long ancient
tradition that we have in India
no burials Cremations
so once again we don't have access to
any skeletons from that time
so there's no way of telling I don't
know what Google is telling you or what
various websites are telling you they
they have no way of knowing what the
average Lifestyle lifespan was uh we
have certain burials from the Indus
Valley Valley Saraswati Hindu Iraq
uh in Western India Northern India
certain symmetries have been found
certain burials have been found once
again the question that is raised is
where these actual representatives of
the population of that time
the the average Indian population or was
where these burials the burials of first
generation immigrants into India
that's also a question that has to be
addressed and we still don't have the
answer
so
so because of all these factors there is
absolutely no way of knowing what the
average lifespan of Indians was during
these ancient time periods there's
simply no way of knowing the only the
only hints and clues that we have is
from ancient literature from the
Mahabharata from the ramayan those texts
and the various uh other upanishads
maybe The Vedas also perhaps if there
are any clues in there so for that you
would have to read these texts to study
these texts Analyze This these texts in
great detail to try and find any clues
or hints I'm not sure if anybody has
done that and that's a job for
historians to do but clearly they have
not done any of these things so the so
because of all this what I just
explained the answer is we simply do not
know but most likely
ancient India most likely the lifespans
must have been significant long-lived
people because the lifestyle was
healthier the diet was there was no
processed food it was much better diet
than what people eat these days pizzas
and burgers and whatnot yeah and
there was an incredible amount of
prosperity in in Ancient India we know
that so because of these factors I would
imagine that the life life spans would
have been very long maybe in excess of
75 80 perhaps even 90 the average but we
don't know for sure
saurabh says in article published in
cell authored by Dr neeraj David Reich
wasn't shinde etc etc which in brief
states that the Indus Valley
Civilization population was has no
detectable ancestry from step
pastoralists or from Anatolian or and
Iranian farmers
this suggests that farming in India
arose independently rather than
large-scale migrations from the West
what's your opinion about this so I had
neeraj on my podcast I think last year
it's been a while and we discussed this
so if you want to know what the facts
are you can look at the podcast so this
paper tells you that
we have found lots of skeletons
from this time period in Western India
in haryana
ETC and they were able to extract DNA
from at least one of these skeletons
they tried from multiple they were able
to extract DNA from one skeleton and
what you find is that there is no
absolutely no uh ancestry from the step
pastoralists or the so-called Iranian
Farmers Anatolian Farmers all that which
means that this was a properly unmixed
population
and a significant amount of Indian of
ancestry of modern day Indians comes
from this ancient population uh
and yeah the
the the the this paper also also
demonstrates that farming arose
independently in India
around the same time
or maybe before it arose in Anatolia or
or with the Iranian Farmers or
whatsoever so this makes it very clear
that in India
the beginning of all these analysis
we're gonna be able to extract more DNA
from more samples and we're going to
have more information in the coming uh
years
so what this is going to tell you is
that India is the most ancient
civilization in the world we know that
India has had farming 17 500 years
before today
at a time when Sri Lanka was still
attached to India because of the Ice Age
and the water the ocean levels were at
least 100 meters below what they are
today so at that time Sri Lanka was
physically a part of the Indian
subcontinent it was not an island
isolated separate Island it was part of
the English Department 17 500 years ago
we have evidence of cultivation in Sri
Lanka
and 11 12 000 years ago Lahore diva in
up Etc there is ample evidence of the
fact that farming and cultivation of
crops arose in India well before the
so-called Fertile Crescent or or
whatever it is that they call it right
so uh it doesn't surprise me and I am
actually waiting for more results from
from Dr neeraj Rai and his team because
uh yeah it's it's going to be
interesting so a lot a lot more research
is happening but what you are mentioning
over here is not surprising at all we
already had evidence of this and this
new result which was published simply
strengthens and corroborates what we
already knew
used to be from Indonesia says is there
really a connection between Greece unani
in Bahasa Indonesia from Ionia and Yona
Java and Yunnan in the China because
according to Indonesian folklore for
some reason Indonesia's ancestors left
India and once inhabited the irawati in
Mekong the maganga rivers
there are lots of names of places in
Indonesia that are thick with nuances of
Saka culture like
Etc these names have been maintained to
this day in the islamicaram Kingdom the
largest Islamic sultanate in Southeast
Asia still uses names from the sakha
culture excellent very interesting
question that you asked
the name of Cambodia okay let's go to
the map
Cambodia is one of the important nations
in Southeast Asia
in case some of us don't know where it
is it is over here
it is east of Thailand south of Laos
west of Vietnam this nation Cambodia
the name Cambodia comes from Cambodia
and there was a Cambodia Dynasty in Iran
and Persia
so there is a connection
between Cambodia and Persia via India
Cambogia right so that's an interesting
uh nugget interesting fact now
uh so according to Indonesian folklore
in the people of Indonesia their
ancestors left India and inhabited the
iravati in mecon rivers regions so if we
look at the people of Indonesia they
look significantly you can you can
clearly see there is an Indian ancestral
element in most of them you can clearly
see that in the name of Indonesia is
Indonesia right so um yes the folklore
is that the the ancestors of the people
of Indonesia are deep in deep Antiquity
came from India and they in settled down
in this huge archipelago and there was a
bit inter mixing between them between
the Indian origin people and the people
who are already living in this region
which gave rise to the modern day
population of Indonesia but the culture
remained significantly Indian and
we had Saka culture in India soccer
culture it refers to the scithians the
scithians used to live in Central Asia
they lived in Central Asia and they
ruled Central Asia for a very long
period of time centuries maybe Millennia
and the scythians themselves were of
Indian origin and they eventually
re-entered India about 2000 years ago so
they left India several thousand years
ago they settled down in Central Asia
ruled Central Asia and then they
re-entered India some 2000 years ago so
it was a round trip Journey for the
suckers the scithians
um and it is possible that some of them
eventually through India
so this kittens who and re-entered India
2000 years ago roughly they assimilated
very harmless harmoniously very rapidly
into the Indian population it is very
likely that lots of people in northern
and western India have some scithian
ancestry but you can't tell
you simply can't tell same both of the
questions and eventually some of them
because of trade and other activities
would have would have made their way
into into Indonesia
because of which
some of the place names Etc in Indonesia
would possibly have skition or Saka
Origins
um and when it comes to Greece see in
India we have always called the Greeks
yavanas right the yavanas what does
yavana mean it means the ionians there
is something called the ionian sea can
we see this here the ionian sea it's
between southern Italy and Greece
and these are the ionian islands over
here
very beautiful islands including
kefalonia Etc
so the Greeks were called ionians and
the word for ionians in India was yavana
now uh we obviously have yavadweep which
is Java is there a connection between
the iodians the yabanas and the
yavadweep I don't know for sure our
historians have not bothered to look
into this and answer this question but
that's a very interesting question that
our friend Arya pinandita has raised
over here and I think it's something
that historians should look into because
we clearly had a significant Greek
presence indo-greek presence in northern
and western India about 2000 years ago
and those Indo Greeks they never went
back to Greece they became Indian as an
Indian they married among the Indian
population and once again like the
scithians and the kushans lots of people
in northern and western India the
subcontinent would have some Greek
ancestry
and some of them would have traveled to
Indonesia for trade and other activities
uh cultural activities trade activities
as teachers as gurus maybe as merchants
so once again there could be some
connection between the name of this
island Java
and the
word for the Greeks yavanas or unani
Yunnan also means yavana right so I
don't have the answers because our
historians have done no Research into
this and this is something that really
needs to be investigated the Deep
connections between India and Southeast
Asia and India and Greece via Persia and
Central Asia it's all interconnected
these are not separate religion regions
that never communicated with each other
everything is interconnected you go go
back two three thousand years you will
find connections between everything
including connections between central
Asia and Indonesia Greece and Indonesia
um and and so on and the center of it
all was India and also Persia but mostly
India very interesting question
unfortunately we don't have the answers
but I am so glad that you've raised
these questions and I wish historians
would take up these very interesting
topics instead of wasting time studying
the so-called mughals
says historically France and Britain
were enemies so why did they fight
together in the Great War and what is
the current situation what was the
atmosphere like before the two great
Wars yes I have a video on this channel
which talks about a thousand thousand
years of enmity between France and
Britain and in English so yes the enmity
between the French and the English goes
back at least a thousand years at least
to the time of the uh Invasion the
Norman invasion of the British Islands
led by Duke William who came to be
eventually known as William the
Conqueror
which was in the year 1066. so at least
a thousand years of enmity then they've
seen many wars
the question is why did the fight
together in the Great War which is World
War One
so the world war one was an extremely
complicated affair
uh if I try to explain all the the the
the scenario properly it would take me
at least half an hour but the thing is
that they had a common enemy the common
enemy was Germany that's let me
oversimplify it and say that the common
enemy was Germany the Germans did invade
France and the Brit the British had to
come to France's rescue
uh
so it was also something that benefited
the British because if France Falls to
Germany then Britain will be next it'll
be threatened so because of that they
had to come together Ally together
against Germany the Germans actually
wanted Britain to be on their side it's
a very complicated mess okay World War
One
I I actually have a detailed podcast
with ranveer alabadya on the beer biceps
channel in which we have discussed the
world war one and World War II
situations so if you are interested in
knowing the details take a look at that
podcast uh so that's why they fought
together in World War one and they were
you could say allies in World War II
obviously the French lost very rapidly
to Germany in World War II to the German
Blitzkrieg and they were very rapidly
occupied by Germany in World War II in
World War One the situation was
significantly different
the current situation is that France and
England or France and the UK are both
U.S vasals
okay so it doesn't matter right now they
are both the same on the same side and
they're put together and held together
in place by the Americans the entirety
of Western Europe is owned occupied or
controlled in some way or the other
either of these three things by The
Americans
Western Europe is a buffer zone that the
Americans created
is a bulwark against Soviet expansion
and now it is a bulwark against Russia
so NATO and the European Union are
essentially controlled and you could say
owned by the Americans the real power in
Western Europe is the United States of
America it is not Germany or France or
the UK it is the USA
so the situation today is that France
and Germany are on the same side because
their boss
ensures that it is so once
the U.S Empire the Anglo-Saxon Saxon
Empire declines and relinquishes its
hold on Europe Europe is going to go
back to its regular routine of fighting
each other
right now it's not so so the peace has
been maintained in Europe for the past
70 or so years because of the U.S
American Supremacy invest in Europe
eventually when the American Empire
declines you're gonna see Europe go back
to war like they have been doing for
centuries
descendant of Rigby Clans says recent
happiness index claims Ukraine and
Russia are much happier than Bharat
including Global terrorism index bharath
is ranked at 13 you are right they
launched their propaganda tools so all
of these things are merely propaganda
let's take a look at the world happiness
index let's see what India is on that
it's it's it's really funny actually
this is the world happiness happiness
trust social connection all that all
that all that stuff uh let us see the
rankings which they have provided
Finland is the happiest station Denmark
ice
Finland is the happiest Nation
uh one second yeah Denmark comes next in
Iceland Israel Netherlands Sweden Norway
Switzerland Luxembourg New Zealand
Austria one thing all these nations have
in common Austria Australia Canada
Ireland us Germany Belgium
you United Kingdom Lithuania France
Slovenia Costa Rica Romania all these
nations from 1 to 24 that you see on the
screen right now
these are all U.S vessels
these are all U.S vasaras do you
understand that
I I kid you not
let's go a little bit more
then you have UAE Taiwan Uruguay
Slovakia Saudi Arabia Estonia Spain
Italy Kosovo Chile Mexico Malta Panama
Nicaragua
Latvia Bahrain Guatemala up to Guatemala
it's all nations that are under U.S
Dominion Kazakhstan is more like in
their in the under Russian it's part of
the Russian zone of influence and so on
so where does India figure I think India
will figure way down India is it number
India is number 126 from the happiness
index oh my God should I start crying I
must be really unhappy then
okay above India you have Liberia a
nation that has been a civil war for for
decades
I I would encourage you not to go to
Google image search and and search for
the Civil War in Liberia horrific images
it's a dirt poor Nation okay Ethiopia oh
man Ethiopia is doing better nowadays
but if you go back to the 1980s there's
this horrific famines in Ethiopia
created by the West
incredibly
poverty stricken nation is happier than
India apparently Sri Lanka whose economy
is in disrepair it's in a shambles
economy is gone
there are shortages of all essential
Commodities in Sri Lanka they are
happier than India apparently
Pakistan is happier than India the
global epicenter of terrorism the people
there are apparently happier than India
so what I can Iraq a nation that was
destroyed by the U.S twice once in 9192
the other time in 2003 or somewhere
around that two oil Wars they bombed
Iran into dust sorry Iraqi to dust they
flattened Baghdad through their bombing
campaigns killed at least a million
human beings and they say that nation
which is still
reeling from the U.S destruction they
said that nation is happier than India
these rankings are a complete joke okay
this is all propaganda
where is China I wonder
China China China China where is China
China is at 64 apparently yeah how nice
I'm sure the Chinese must have paid
these guys through the Deep Pockets now
let's take a look at this which is a
treat about this the world's happiest
country is Finland Denmark Iceland
Israel all that same thing
let's take a look at the Tweet by Nasim
Nicholas taleb
take a look at this
he says busting means of today
we cannot scientifically measure
happiness and make cross-cultural
comparisons but we can measure and
compare the suicide rate which happens
to be high in these so-called happy
places Never Trust claims by
psychologists
there you have it the fact is that when
you list countries by suicide rates
you will find that most of the so-called
extremely happy countries have very high
suicide rates
very high suicide rates they say let's
once again where is this they say Japan
where is Japan in this list Japan is not
really high it's at 47 but if you look
at Finland Denmark Iceland these nations
have extremely high suicide rates and
when it comes to
India India has one of the lowest
suicide rates in the world and yet India
is one of the unhappiest Nations
so these claims
don't make any sense this is all
propaganda listen to what nothing Talib
says he he makes a huge amount of sense
these nations
have they happen to have very high
suicide rates so that itself tells you
that these rankings are all arbitrary
they're all made up and they're all
propaganda and keeping India at number
120 whatever it is it's a complete joke
complete joke India is one of the most
optimistic populations in the world and
the optimism is grounded in reality
because India's economy is the only
economy that's going to keep on growing
in the next 20 30 40 years Every Other
Nation is now declining every major
nation is declining what's happening to
China what's happening to all these
Nordic Nations which are which are
number one number to number three number
ten
their economies are not doing well
India is the nation that's going to keep
on Rising so uh all of this what you are
seeing let's not get swayed by it let's
not believe this nonsense it is all
propaganda all right let us not believe
this propaganda
says why is credited
by scholars in case some of us don't
know the rajatarangini is an is a poem
it's a historical poem written by the
kashmiri uh historian kalahana it's
about the record of of the history of
Kashmir
okay it's about the history of Kashmir
uh but it's obviously if it's a history
of Kashmir it's a history of India so
let's take a look at what the print has
to say about kalhana in the
rajatarangini
so this is what the print the print have
to say does narrative of 5000 years of
Hindu history and Kashmir need
challenging why does it need challenging
so let's say so this is the responses
are by various people so this is by
Khalid Bashir Ahmad
according to Khalid Bashir Ahmad
uh
he says that uh Kashmir is known to have
to have in an uninterrupted history of
five millionaire
his narrative is strikingly precise to a
couple of centuries prior to his own
time but incredibly fictional for the
first 3000 years so Mr Khalid Ahmad is
saying that India's history of the first
thousand years of the Raj tarangini is
incredibly fictional
uh it's a description of persons and
events entrance untrained untraceable in
other sources
the author himself alludes to using his
Mind's Eye in composing his work while
crashing all the other 11 sorts of
History
file for misplaced learning so this
gentleman Khalid Bashir Ahmad says that
this is all fiction
um
Rahul pandita says that the truth is on
our side in the form of the sun Temple
so Rahul pandita says that this the
history has the kalhana rajatarangini
history has to be trusted because it is
factual
classes is an unbiased clear historical
writing without any pressure from the
Kings
Center for Central Asian studies
University of Kashmir says uh yeah
Buddhism and Hinduism were never at
loggerheads in Kashmir
uh all that
Baba professor of political science
Kashmir University says that the Raj
tarangini is an exclusivist vision of
kashmir's History it's been used to suit
a certain hegemonic account of the past
uh
and so on
so so what you see is that certain
people want to portray the Raj tarangini
is hegemonic and fictional
but overall you see that it's one of the
most uh
one of the most expansive
accounts of ancient Indian history so
the scholars the the it's a few Scholars
with a certain ideological mindset
typically a leftist mindset they are the
ones who seek to discredit the Raj
tarangini they said there is no evidence
for what is being claimed in the
rajdarangini
well the evidence was all been destroyed
there would have been copious amounts of
supporting evidence which you would have
found in the great libraries of the
ancient Indian universities but all
these universities were destroyed and
the libraries burned about A Thousand
Years Ago by the invading Turks so
nothing of that is left so somehow the
Raj tamangini has survived but because
we don't have any supporting literary
evidence so it is being discredited as
being fiction
so my opinion is that this is all a
proper historical account and it's a
it's an incredibly valuable historical
account of the past five thousand years
of Indian history and kashmiri history
so certain people will keep on trying to
discredit discredit everything good
so if you look at the Raj tarangini it
talks about
essentially it begins from the
Mahabharata
and it gives entire lists of lineages of
kings and dynasties that you will not
find anywhere else because everything
else has been destroyed so it's
incredibly valuable source of
information of the various Kings and
dynasties and rulers and queens that
ruled and administered and enriched
India in the past the innovators tried
to destroy all this information
so that they can portray India as a as
an a historical and pathetic place but
because the Raj darangania survived that
narrative has been well it's not quite
succeeded so they are trying to now
discredit the Raj dharangini and
discredit kalhana himself let us not get
swayed by this propaganda
Krishna says why did the Nazis flee to
Argentina so after the end of the second
world war the Nazis were defeated
Germany was occupied by half of it by
the Soviets half of it by the Americans
and
the Americans obviously had to demonize
the Nazis for good reasons and for not
good reasons obviously the Nazis
conducted the genocide of the Romani
people and the Jewish people so clearly
that's extreme evil and obviously Hitler
was extremely evil uh
so they had to make public examples of
many of these people many of these
Nuremberg trials Etc and many of these
Nazi leaders were put to death they were
hanged there were other executions you
know summary summary Justice on the
battlefield or after the battle a lot of
that happened
so many of these Nazis
were very valuable
they were very competent people they had
great skills think about someone like
Werner von Braun
Brown is the father of the U.S space
program
he was a pioneering rocket scientist
he's the guy who developed the V1 and V2
Rockets the first cruise missile and the
first ballistic missile of all time and
he developed this in Germany to do that
here to be part of the Nazi war machine
so he was an extremely valuable asset
and then the Americans took him to the
US and they put him in charge of various
things eventually he was in charge of
these Saturn V rocket program which put
the few first human beings on the moon
so he is one example of a very valuable
Nazi
there were lots of others
okay the Nazi war machine the Nazi
Administration
it was evil for sure but it was
extremely competent extremely efficient
that's a lot of talent a huge amount of
talent
and the Americans they don't want to
waste on the talent so lots of these
Nazis they were given safe refuge in
Argentina let's understand the Americans
had the Monroe Doctrine it still
continues which means North America and
South America can only be under U.S
control and domination
so if something was happening in
Argentina it is impossible the Americans
did not know about this and if Nazis
were being transported all the way from
Europe
all the way across the Atlantic Ocean to
South America it wouldn't it is
impossible to imagine this would happen
without the Americans knowing about it
so people like Adolf Eichmann uh that
evil doctor Mengele and lots of other
Nazis made their way into Argentina
Argentina gave them safe Refuge
and it's possible that the that some of
them even provided certain services to
more powerful Nations because they were
very competent people so Argentina gave
them Refuge other nations in other
organizations we don't know who they may
or may not be maybe great Powers they
gave them safe Passage
so that all the Nazis don't get
destroyed and the talent can be used in
some way or the other
this is I mean we don't know for sure
what happened who did all this but it's
clear that lots of prominent Nazis ended
up in Argentina so Argentina gave them
safe refuge and somehow these guys got
safe passage across such large distances
okay a big guy says what do you think
about the cigar-shaped Oddity from outer
space
was it artificial as it had no Comet
Tail okay let's put umua on the screen
shall we give me a second
on the screen
so it is depicted as something that
looks like like it has a cigar shape
here we are
so this was a visitor from outer space
that that uh
passed through the solar system through
the inner solar system
I think in 27 yeah it says 2017. so it
was detected after it already it had
already gone around the Sun achieved its
closest distance to the sun and it was
already speeding out of the solar system
by this time
uh so this is the kind of trajectory it
took and it was detected when it was
already going past the orbit of the
earth and it was like about 80 lunar
distances away from the earth that's
when it was detected it had already made
its uh closest approach to the sun and
it was traveling at incredibly High
Velocity which means that it was passing
through the solar system only once and
mostly and it will never return the the
trajectory is hyperbolic not parabolic
or circular or whatever or elliptical
sorry yeah it's a hyperbolic trajectory
as far as I remember so why is this
curious so there are certain things
about this object which make it very
unusual first of all it is at least 10
times as long as it is Broad and you
don't ever find any asteroid or space
rock or Comet that has such dimensions
so let's say it's a it's a hundred
meters long and 10 meters wide at most
it's a very long and thin object that is
one strange thing about it that's like
one in a thousand kind of
characteristics at least
secondly
it is it was extremely reflective
it gave off a lot of light
which was reflected sunlight was being
reflected from this thing's surface it
was so reflective that it looked like it
was made of polished metal
it was at least minimum 10 times more
reflective than your regular space rocks
that's the second thing which is strange
about this object
the third thing
is that it accelerated away from the Sun
typically if a space Rock goes around
the Sun the
You can predict the the speed at which
it goes away based on the speed at which
it approached its simple mathematics and
Newton's Laws now this thing
it actually accelerated away from the
Sun
it did not go in a constant uh speed
there was acceleration as if there is a
rocket jet behind it of some kind but as
it went further from the Sun the
acceleration decreased
as the inverse square of the as the
inverse square of the distance from the
sun which is very strange it's like an
inverse power low kind of thing
so now we have certain objects that
behave like this they are called comets
okay we have comments that accelerate
away from the sun because the sun makes
the the of the body the
the body of the Comet it heats up and it
ejects water vapor and dust and gas out
of it which makes the comet accelerate
but comets they accelerate unevenly
there are gaps in fissures in the Rock
and these Jets come out in unexpected
directions so that's why the
acceleration is stop and start in the
case of a comet but in case of um it was
a smooth dark celebration very smooth
acceleration
as if you have an actual rocket engine
behind it
nobody saw in rocket engine but and then
they tried to look for carbon dioxide
and gas and dust through very through
the Spitzer Space Telescope and other
telescopes not
not
anything nothing was detected
so in the case of a comet when it's
accelerating they can see why it's
accelerating because you have this
entire common tail behind it which is
pushing the comet forward and
accelerating the combat in the case of
nothing was detected detected no
ejection of of dust or or water vapor or
in or carbon dioxide or anything was
edited at all
so he doesn't somehow accelerating but
there was no mechanism that could
account for the acceleration
so it's like a one in a million kind of
object
uh
so the the the physicist Avi Lube the
Israeli physicist I believe he said that
this is behaving like a solar cell
so uh so there are two possible shapes
that this object could have had one is a
cigar shape and the other is a pancake
pancake shape
okay
so pancake also from the side it will
look like a cigar
if it was pancake shaped if it was
metallic then that can
that can
um explain the acceleration the
acceleration will be because of solar
radiation
it's called radiation pressure radiation
itself can make you make a solar seal
accelerate you know uh
so let me show you what a solar cell
looks like let's put this back on the
screen
solar sale
so this is what a solar cell looks like
and this is accelerated and propelled
merely by sunlight by the radiation
pressure of sunlight
so if umua was a solar cell that would
totally explain
its acceleration and the fact that the
acceleration slowed down the further it
was away from the Sun
so it was highly reflective so
reflective that it could have been made
of polished metal metal
it was possibly a disc shaped object
which is the shape kind of like a solar
sail and its acceleration
was again something that can be
explained By Its So by it being a solar
sale
so yeah all of these factors they make
it look like this could have been very
much artificial but obviously we have no
actual evidence for this we only have
some data and this data is very strange
okay but when this guy Avi Lube spoke
about this he wrote I think he wrote a
book about this
so he was ridiculed by the scientific
Community which then which tends to be
extremely uh conservative but I think it
makes kind of it kind of makes sense
what he has said what is spoken about
this and written about this
so yeah we don't know for sure what it
was but its behavior and its properties
were very strange and they can't really
be explained
unless you you think of it as a solar
Sail
yeah
so princes what are what is the
intermediate Mass black hole in uh and
we are yet to find evidence for its
existence do we have I think they have
found some intermediate Mass black holes
if I'm not mistaken uh so what's an
intermediate boss black hole so we we
typically have observed two kinds of
black holes one is the Stellar Mass
black hole
which is typically three to ten times
mass of our sun the sun
so typical Stellar Mass black holes are
three to ten times the mass of the Sun
sometimes you could say the upper range
is of a hundred solar masses that's your
Stellar Mass black hole and then you
have supermassive black holes which are
typically a million times and more than
the Sun's mass
so these Stellar size black hole it is
born from the
explosive depth of a star in a Super
Robot explosion some mechanisms show
that it can the star can even become a
black hole without ever undergoing a
supernova explosion that's possible the
storm is just wink out of existence
suddenly go dark that would happen so
that's how a supermassive black hole is
typically formed at the end of a
supernova explosion and supermassive
black holes are
we don't quite know how they were formed
but they exist and we have observed them
they typically live at the heart of
every Galaxy our own galaxy The Milky
Way has a supermassive black hole at its
heart at its Center
and there is another kind of black hole
that is hypothesis never seen the
primordial microscopic black holes that
may have been formed in enormous
quantities in the immediate aftermath of
the Big Bang but we haven't observed
them yet so now there is one candidate
black hole which is called the
intermediate Mass black hole which whose
Mass lies between
100 solar masses at the lower limit and
a million solar masses at the upper
limit typically something like a ten
thousand hundred thousand solar mass is
kind of mass range but there is no
mechanism by which such black holes can
be formed that we know of
so that's what it is and that's the
missing Gap but these days I think
astronomers and uh instruments have
detected certain black holes like
there's one which was detected at the
heart of a certain Galaxy it should have
been a supermassive black hole but it
was actually an intermediate Mass black
hole like 10 000 floral masses kind of
thing which is squarely in the in in the
intermediate Mass black hole range so
it's still a mystery how such black
holes could exist we don't know of any
mechanism that can explain the formation
of a black hole of that mass even
supermassive black holes we're not quite
sure how they would form one mechanism
is that a black hole is formed in the
very early universe and it merges with
other black holes in in sucks in lots of
uh material from other stars and
whatever it is and eventually it
accretes and grows larger that's one
mechanism but will will it reach that
supermassive mass in the amount of time
the universe has existed lots of
questions abound so that's why
intermediate Mass black holes are kind
of a mystery I think we have observed at
least two or three of these thus far but
we're not quite sure how they would have
been created informed because we don't
know of any mechanism that can reliably
create such black holes so that's why
it's it's a mystery
deep Angela says after listening to you
I can relate and I lost my interest in
this kind of education I it was never my
intention to make people lose interest
in education
okay so she says that everything feels
boring about it and now I hate it how
would I even prepare for the IIT or
others if I know the preparation or that
these are not useful outside the
academic campus can you discuss some
career options for science students and
guide more realistically okay look
a long time ago I I bought a few
self-help books like 20 years ago okay
there was this one that I remember it's
by a guy called I think it was Stephen
Tracy or something like that his name
was and then books book's name was eat
that frog
I think it's still lying around
somewhere in my house
eat that frog so the books central idea
is that at the beginning of the day when
you wake up and you are about to get to
work
you should eat the Frog which means they
do the most unpleasant thing first get
it out of the way so that you can have a
nice day after that so today if I have
five tasks to do and one of them is
extremely is is exceptionally unpleasant
and difficult do that first get it over
with if it is important
so similarly if you want to have a good
career and a good life whether you like
it or not a good degree matters
so
you have to motivate yourself by telling
yourself I am going to have a successful
life and career
and for that a good degree matters so
that's why you should go through it
sometimes you have to do unpleasant
things in order to enjoy success in the
long run
so and you you know what
whatever
Knowledge and Skills you acquire in the
iits these are actually going to be
useful outside the academic campus let's
say hypothetically you do mechanical
engineering with that degree and with
those skills you can help the nation by
building roads roads and bridges and
Railway infra infrastructure you can
actually contribute a lot to the nation
with those skills let's say you do a
degree in mechanical let's say
Aeronautical Engineering you can start
an aeronautical company or you can join
ISRO and work with in rocket design you
know in the beginning when the rocket is
going up it has to go through the
atmosphere in that aeronautical design
comes in very handy you can design
airplanes you can design fighter planes
there is so much you can do so
engineering is applied science it has a
huge amount of applications outside the
academic campus
you can truly contribute to the nation
and you can truly become successful and
prosperous and Rich with these skills
that you acquire in the iits saying goes
with computer engineering computer
science all these things there are so
many of the skills that are actually
valuable and they can really be deployed
effectively in real life and they can
contribute to yourself to your success
in in prosperity and to that of the
nation
so for science students especially in
the engineering
applied sciences uh domain these skills
are extremely valuable
so I would say please focus on these
things especially if you have an
inclination towards science if you're
good at science you should definitely do
this
these skills will be valuable
and as the nation grows as the economy
grows more jobs will be needed more
skilled people will be needed we need to
build an enormous amount of
infrastructure we need to build so much
we have we are a 3.5 trillion dollars we
need to reach at least 10 trillion
dollars in the next 10 years that's and
by 2050 we have to be the world's
largest economy it will happen only
through the the skills and the knowledge
that you acquire through degrees in
places like the iits the nits and all
that so I think it's very exciting if
you are trying to get into the IIT I
think you should really motivate
yourself that you can really do a whole
lot of good with such skills and
knowledge and degree and it should
totally plunge into the preparation it's
exciting and when you're preparing
you're competing against your peers
isn't that fun I mean why do we enjoy
sports because it's competition let's
see who's the best so why don't you do
it and show who's the best yeah so I
think you should not be demotivated like
this the problems in the education
system lie in the humanities in the
so-called social non-sciences
in in history these in in literature
that's where the education system is
totally rotten in science it's much
better especially the iits and the NIT
Etc they still have reasonably good
standards there are issues there also
but once you get the knowledge and the
skills and the degree you can do a lot
of good so please don't be demoralized
demotivated go for it and go succeed and
contribute to the nation all right all
the best
monish says how to prevent the
resistance we will face if the education
system is reformed by actual in the
actual means we have faced so much
backlash during Pharma protests Etc how
to prevent it
yes that's a good example you give the
backlash during the farmer protests all
these protesters
orchestrated by external forces which
have a lot of control of of let's say
certain media outlets and possibly
perhaps certain possibly political
parties within India possibly Perhaps it
is a possibility definitely lots of
media Outlets are controlled or are
funded from from abroad so they were
able to create a narrative
and whatever uh
activities happened on the streets
these are also organized well organized
and well funded
and they they sought to paralyze Delhi
and other parts of Northern India Etc to
make it look like this enormous form of
rut is happening and you had various
influencers who were supporting this so
it kind of Brainwashed the entire public
into believing the farm laws are
terrible for India nobody actually read
the farm laws and tried to examine what
these laws were so
so lies were able to succeed and why
were they able to succeed is because the
government of India
chose not to crush these protests
the Indian government
has the control of the entire State
machinery
State as in the state the nation state
of India
the Indian government the central
government could have crushed these
protests if it's so desired it shows not
to why did it choose not to because the
moment you take any action
you know through the police against
these protests and clear the roads to
the streets and you know all that you're
gonna have some violence and all that
stuff because they have they want that
the protesters have been told to provoke
the government into violence so once you
do that the entire world will start
it's bigger propaganda of portraying
India as as a fascist Nation as an
undemocratic Nation all that so from the
big picture long-term perspective it was
the government decided that let this go
on and let it die its own natural death
and they actually withdrew the farm laws
because the big picture and the long
term
of the uh the long-term picture is more
important than anything you do in the
short term so similarly if Indian go
India's government decides to
genuinely reform the education system
there's going to be the same sort of
thing that's going to happen
they're gonna claim
that India is now going backwards it is
it is interfering in education it's
trying to brainwash people when actually
the reverse is happening we're gonna
actually clean up the education so this
is not the right time for this so I did
say earlier in this live stream that I
am very disappointed about the fact that
the education system has not been
reformed but I kind of understand why
it's so this is not the right time
when will it be the right time when
India is much more powerful than what it
is today right now there are other
forces that are way more powerful than
us and they can well they can hurt us in
a lot of ways
by tarnishing India's reputation by
making it hard for India for for Indians
to travel abroad because your your seen
as as belonging to a nation that is
um undemocratic and which doesn't really
respect human rights and all that so
it's going to be difficult so right now
we're trying to have as little friction
as possible and focusing on the big
things which is economic growth
eventually once we are at a certain Mark
maybe the 10 trillion dollar Mark we
will go and do this and tell the world
to take a hike
so it's all about doing the right thing
at the right time and certain things for
certain things perhaps the right time is
not now so I even though it is
disappointing for me personally that the
education system which is in such a big
mess is not being reformed I still do
understand why it is not being touched
right now because this is most likely
not the right time to take up that fight
that fight will be taken up at the at an
appropriate time in the future
all right we are we have crossed the two
hour mark let's take some other
questions I as always I have a whole lot
more questions which I will not be able
to take
what shall I take
um
interesting sahib haha says what's the
history of the violin is it somehow
related related to the ravanatha I I am
pretty sure that almost nobody in India
knows what the ravantha is the violin
has a 500 year history the earliest
appearance of the violin or violin like
bowed instruments in in art in painting
Etc it goes back about 500 years at most
in Europe the violin is a European
instrument maybe it came via the Arabic
or Islamic World perhaps but let's take
a look at the ravan Hatha
foreign
let me put that on the screen so this is
a very ancient instrument
that we've had
in India
let's put this on the screen this is a
very ancient bowed instrument which is
played in this in the in a in the same
way as the violin but it's way more
ancient than the violin and you find it
being used in the folk music of northern
and western India
typically it is a Rajasthani musicians
who played the ravana and sing the folk
songs and all that very melodious very
very very nice sounding instrument
uh it's a four it's it's termed as a
folk instrument
and it is played
you know in much the same way that that
you would play the violin and it's
clearly way more ancient
than the violin what does Wikipedia have
to say about this let's see it's an
ancient bowed string instrument used in
all the Indian subcontinent it has been
suggested as an ancestor of the violin
so what could have happened we know that
a thousand years ago the Islamic world
the the Turks and the Arabs Etc they
came to India seeking knowledge they
took out all the knowledge before
destroying the Indian universities and
libraries and they would have also come
across the Indian instruments such as
the ravanatha and they would have taken
these instruments to the um to the
Arabic Islamic turkic World whatever
and
and what could have happened is that
this would have this instrument would
have then given rise to the various
about instruments in the Arabic or
Islamic world like the RAB Etc and
eventually this all made its way into
Europe so these Islamic uh Scholars or
translators Etc Travelers they got
access to India about a thousand years
ago
so it makes sense that by the 11th or
12th century these instruments were
prevalent in the Islamic world in the
form of the rhabdab or whatever they
they converted that into and by the 15th
16th century these instruments had made
their way into Europe and they became
the ancestors of the violin it is very
plausible that this is what happened but
once again our historians have not
looked into this so we don't know for
sure there is so much that our
researchers our historians can research
but they
obstinately choose not to they will
simply keep on doing whatever the hell
they've been doing for the past 70 years
I'm sure there are a few good ones but I
don't see any real research output about
these topics that are so fascinating
uh
is erdogan's dream of the Ottoman Empire
of a Neo Ottoman Empire shattered
because of the earthquakes do you see
him losing elections this year right so
we recently had these twin earthquakes
in Turkey extremely powerful devastating
earthquakes that have caused a huge
amount of Destruction hundreds of
billions of dollars worth possibly I'm
not sure what the total figure is but
very high uh destruction
huge economic damage lots of people died
also India responded very rapidly India
said one of the biggest Medical
contingents in search and rescue
continues to Turkey and we did what we
could
we were one of the First Responders and
one of the biggest responders to this
humanitarian crisis uh so large parts of
Northern turkey Etc have been totally
devastated and
the first responses typically you know
saving human lives and given medical
treatment so that stage is gone now
nobody whoever is buried there under the
rubble it's impossible they would have
survived until now so they rescuing
human lives the stage is gone and all
the injuries most of the injuries would
be treated treated by now and all the
lives that could be saved have been
saved the real work begins now
reconstructing the destroyed
city is down Etc in turkey that's going
to take a long time and people are going
to be really really upset and angry that
it's not happening immediately
that's going to be a big challenge for
erdogan so it's going to be a big
challenge for him to retain
his
being in government being in power
and and be real be re-elected as the
president of Turkey this year it's going
to be a big challenge for him and
obviously because of the economic damage
it's going it's definitely going to
affect the Turkish economy
your economy it definitely affects your
military power and all that so yes I
would not say that the dream that the
dream of the Neo Ottoman Empire has been
shattered but it's certainly been it's
received a big setback
I'm sure Mr erdogan will still dream of
you know re creating a new Ottoman
Empire or something like that but yes
it's it's uh definitely these dreams
have definitely received a big setback
for sure
okay a lot more questions I will not
take them now because we're almost at
the end let's take some questions from
the live chat
let's take from the
live chat
Joseph pedophile says what religion
please should I aspire to join I am not
a fan of abrahamic religions because
they are misogynistic and racist as an
atheistic male as an atheist male can I
join Hinduism dharmic religion thanks
listen it's it's it's it's going to come
from you it's going to come from your
heart what are you most attracted
towards what are you drawn towards
um if you are an atheistic person if you
don't believe in God clearly you cannot
join any of the abrahamic religions
because it is mandatory to belong to
believe in the abrahamic god in those
religions so the abrahamic religions
clearly are out now when it comes to the
dharmic religions you can be in atheist
and be be and live with dharmic
lifestyle
um for instance in in the in the dharmik
umbrella of religions or or
philosophical schools of thought which
is all part of Hinduism there is this
path called The charwaka Path which is
an atheistic part materialistic path and
it's definitely still part of Hinduism
so you can be an atheist and be a Hindu
for sure even a Jain or a Buddhist even
if you're atheist so and obviously there
are other parts also like like Shinto
which is kind of like the Japanese form
of Hinduism much more complex than
Japanese Buddhism for sure then you have
tengirism if you if you are inclined
towards the Mongolian uh culture
tangerism again it's a polytheistic uh
belief system very similar to Hinduism
once again which is why it was so easy
for Mongolia to absorb Indian culture
then you have Tao you have Confucianism
which is all atheism uh you have
Zoroastrianism which is the polytheistic
uh belief system which which is now
portrait is monotheistic and so much
more so I think it's entirely up to you
what you what resonates most with you
and uh
yeah so the the the
religious path that accepts and welcomes
and respects everybody is the dharmic
thought which is nowadays called
Hinduism which includes and this is
controversial But it includes Buddhism
Jainism and sexism as well so it's
entirely up to you and you have to find
your the right answer so I can give you
some
choices but at the end of the day it has
to be your choice your decision
okay okay let us let us
seven says you said you love pakistanis
I said I have nothing against the people
of Pakistan I do not wish to see them
suffer
okay I wish to see the Pakistani people
are after all our relatives they are the
descendants of our own ancestors they're
our own cousins and I do not wish any
human being any harm or sadness or
suffering or misery or pain
so I will repeat this I have nothing
against the people of Pakistan I would
like to see them happy in their own way
whatever way is best they they feel is
best for them let them be happy let them
succeed let their children be happy and
prosperous I have nothing against them
but the nation state of Pakistan has to
be dealt with and dismantled because it
is a terrorist nation in the root cause
of the terrorism is the Pakistani army I
have never said that I love the
pakistanis I said that I I wish them
well that's what I have said all right
all right I think we will stop over here
it's two hours 11 12 minutes
um well past our usual limit so we're
gonna end over here this session thank
you very much as always for all the
wonderful questions as always I have not
been able to take all the questions and
there are thousands more so thank you so
much I really appreciate it I am really
honored that you asked me so many
questions and I will keep on taking as
many as I can in future episodes thank
you very much take care keep working
hard keep raising your standards and I
will see you very soon thank you good
day good day goodbye see you soon